Guide to the Roy and Clara Creighton Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Roy and Clara Creighton Papers
1908-1972
RG 177
Yale University Divinity School Library
2.5
(5 boxes)
Consisting primarily of correspondence between the Creightons and family members in the U.S., this collection provides valuable detailed information about Roy Creighton's work, the life of a typical missionary wife, and the complications of raising a family on the mission field. Roy Creighton was an American architect who supervised the construction of buildings on the mission field. He served under the YMCA and Presbyterian Board in China, at the American University of Beirut in Lebanon, and Robert College in Turkey. He also taught at the Engineering School of the College of Chinese Studies. Clara Creighton was a missionary wife and homemaker.
Creighton, Roy, 1889-1974
Creighton, Clara, 1892-1978
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Roger L. Creighton
Biographical / Historical
1889 Roy Lamont Creighton born
1892 Clara Linn born
1915 After graduation from Harvard, RLC went to Hangchow, China as a Building Supervisor for the YMCA
1916 Jan Move to Hankow
1916 Aug CLC came out to China and they were married at Kuling
1917 RLC supervised hospital construction at Boone University, Wuchang
1917 Jun Son, Linn, born
1919-1926 RLC worked for Architects Bureau of the Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. in Shanghai
1920 Furlough in U.S.
1921 Daughter, Marjory, born; died in 1922
1923 Son, Roger, born
1924 Daughter, Phyllis, born
1928 Following furlough in the U.S., the Creightons when to Beirut, Syria (Lebanon) where RLC supervised construction at the American University of Beirut.
1931 Following furlough in the U.S., the Creightons went to Istanbul, Turkey, where RLC supervised the building of a library for Robert College.
1933 Following furlough in the U.S., the Creightons returned to China, based in Peking (Beijing). RLC taught at Engineering School of the College of Chinese Studies and traveled to supervise construction of Presbyterian Mission buildings.
1940 Clara and two younger children evacuated to U.S. due to war conditions; RLC remained in Peking.
1941 Dec RLC interned by Japanese 1943 Dec RLC repatriated to U.S.
1944 RLC working at New York office of Presbyterian Mission Board
1946 RLC to Shanghai to rehabilitate mission properties
1948 RLC and CLC to Shanghai, evacuated to Hong Kong
1950 RLC and CLC in Thailand
1952 RLC and CLC in New York, Presbyterian Board offices
1959 RLC retired
1974 RLC died
1978 CLC died
Scope and Contents
Many of the letters in this collection were published by Roger L. Creighton as a book entitled "84 Randall Ave. The Lives of Roy and Clara Creighton; Letters of 1908-1978" (in YDSL cataloged collection).
These papers provide valuable insight into the work of a missionary architect and building supervisor who worked primarily in China, first for the YMCA and later for the Presbyterian Mission Board. The letters are primarily from the Creightons to their family members in the U.S., at first primarily their parents and siblings, but later their children. Periodic circular letters by the Creightons provide succinct summaries of their work. The letters of Clara Creighton from China provide an excellent record of the daily life of a woman missionary who was primarily a mother and homemaker, including documentation of the social life of mainline Protestant, city-based missionaries.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, with enclosures, 1908-1972
Architects -- China; Missions -- China; Architects; Missionaries; Creighton, Clara, 1892-1978; Creighton, Roy, 1889-1974
- Correspondence, 1908-1972; Series I
  - RLC and CLC to each other and to others; in U.S., 1908-1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - RLC to CLC; in U.S., on journey to China, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - RLC to CLC; from YMCA Hangchow and YMCA Hankow; includes Boone University, Wuchang, 6th Annual Commencement program, 1915 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - RLC to CLC; from Hankow, 1916 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Primarily from RLC in Hankow; arrangements for marriage of RLC and CLC, 1916 May -Jun (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - RLC, CLC to various; journey of CLC to China; marriage in Kuling, 1916 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Kuling, 1916 Sep -Oct (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Hankow, 1916 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Primarily RLC, CLC to various; from Hankow; birth of son (Linn), 1917 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Hankow, Kuling, 1917 Jul -Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Hankow, Kuling, Jan -Aug 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Hankow, Sep-Dec 1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - RLC,CLC to various; from Shanghai, from Hangchow, 1919 Jan- May (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - RLC,CLC to various; from Hangchow, 1919 Jun-Dec (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Return to U.S. on furlough, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Furlough in U.S; return to Hangchow; birth of daughter (Marjory); passport of RLC, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - RLC, CLC to various, from Shanghai; re. death of daughter, 1922 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Kuling, Shanghai; condolences re. death of daughter., 1922 Jul -Dec (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Shanghai; birth of son (Roger), 1923 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Shanghai; circular letter (Feb. 11) gives overview of work with Mission Architects Bureau, news re. bandits, 1924 Jan -Jul (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Peitaho, Peking, Shanghai; re. birth of daughter (Phyllis), 1924 Aug-Dec (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Shanghai; includes pamphlet "Missions and Architecture - Residences" by Charles A. Gunn and Roy L. Creighton, published by the Architects Bureau of the Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A., 1925 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - RLC, CLC to various, from Shanghai; incl. circular letter 1926 Jan 15 re. political events, anti-Christian movement, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from U.S., enroute to Syria, from American University of Beirut, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Beirut, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Beirut, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from U.S., enroute to Turkey, from Robert College, Istanbul; letter from Linn to grandfather, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Robert College, Istanbul, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from U.S., enroute to China; from Hangchow, 1933 Jan-May (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - RLC, CLC, children to various; from Peking, Petaiho, 1933 Jun -Dec (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Peking; Linn to various enroute to US, 1934 Jan -Jul (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Peking, incl. circular letter Dec 1, 1934 Aug -Dec (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - RLC, CLC to various; from Peking, Peitaiho, 1935 Jna-Jun (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - RLC,CLC, to/from Linn and others; from Peking, 1935 Jul-Dec (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - RLC,CLC, to/from Linn and others; from Peking, 1936 Jan -Jun (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - RLC,CLC, to/from Linn and others; from Peking, 1936 Jul -Dec (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - RLC, CLC, to/fr. children and others; from Peking, Peitaiho, 1937 Jan -Aug (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - RLC, CLC to/fr. children and others; from Peking; newspaper clippings re. Sino-Japanese war, 1937 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - RLC, CLC to/fr. children and others; from Peking, return to U.S., 1938 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - RLC, CLC to/fr. children and others; from U.S., return to Peking, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - RLC,CLC to/fr. children and others; from Peking, 1940 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - RLC,CLC to/fr. children and others; from Peking, 1940 May-Dec (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - RLC to family; from Peking; includes newspaper article by Rosamund Frame, text of a talk on missionary children entitled "Children of Two Cultures", 1941 Jan-Apr (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - RLC to family; from Peking, 1941 May -Aug (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - RLC to/from family; family to/from each other; RLC a war prisoner of Japanese following Dec. 7., 1941 Sep -Dec (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Family in U.S. to RLC in internment; mimeographed China Bulletins from Presbyterian Foreign Mission Board re. interned missionaries, 1942 Jan -Mar (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - To/from family members in U.S.and RLC in internment; mimeographed China Bulletin from Presbyterian Foreign Mission Board re. interned missionaries, 1942 Apr-Dec (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - To/from various family members in U.S.and RLC in internment; mimeographed China Bulletins from Presbyterian Foreign Mission Board re. interned missionaries, 1943 Jan -Apr (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - To/from various family members in U.S.and RLC; newspaper clipping re. repatriation of RLC, 1943 May -Dec (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - To/from children; circular letter, February, 1944 Jan -May (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - To/from children, 1944 Jun -Dec (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - To/from children, 1945 Jan -May (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - To/from family members, 1945 Jun -Dec (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - To/from family members, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - To/from family members, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - RLC, CLC to/from family members and Presbyterian church women; from Shanghai, 1948 Jan-May (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - RLC, CLC to/from family members and Presbyterian church women; from Shanghai, 1948 Jun-Dec (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - RLC, CLC to/from family members and Presbyterian church women; from Shanghai and from Hong Kong following May evacuation, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - RLC, CLC to/from family members and Presbyterian church women; from Hong Kong, from Thailand, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - RLC, CLC to/from family members and Presbyterian church women; from Hong Kong, from Thailand, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - RLC, CLC to/from family members and Presbyterian church women; from Hong Kong, from Thailand, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - RLC, CLC to/from family members; from New York, 1953-1957 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - RLC, CLC to/from family members; from New York, Maine, 1958-1962 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - RLC, CLC to/from family members; from Maine, 1963-1967 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - RLC, CLC to/from family members; from Maine, 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 65)